A Guide to the Mutual Fire Insurance Company of Loudoun County Records, 1849-1954
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
The Mutual Fire Insurance Company of Loudoun County Records, 1849-1954
The Library of Virginia
41374
165 cu. ft., 125 volumes, and 6 microfilm reels.
Loudoun Mutual Insurance Company.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
THE COLLECTION IS LOCATED AT THE STATE RECORDS CENTER. CONTACT ARCHIVES RESEARCH SERVICES FOR ACCESS INFORMATION, DIRECTIONS, AND HOURS.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Loudoun Mutual Insurance Company, Waterford, Virginia 20197
Historical Information
The Mutual Fire Insurance Company of Loudoun County was incorporated on 12 March 1849. Its headquarters are in Waterford, Virginia. The first Directors' meeting was held on 25 May 1849, and the company's constitution and by-laws were adopted on 9 June 1849. The company accepted its first application for insurance later that month on 27 June. By the Civil War, the company was conducting business in seventeen Virginia counties, and assets of slightly over $15,000. It suspended operations during the war, but company meetings contintued to be held. A new company office was constructed in 1872, and a larger one was built in 1900. The company wrote policies on houses and farm buildings, as well as alms houses, canning factories, churches, mills, livery stables, banks, and jails. In the 1940's, in addition to fire insurance, the company began to cover damage from wind, hail, explosion, smoke, and on vehicles. The present company headquarters was built in 1948. On 1 March 1979, the name of the company was changed to the Loudoun Mutual Insurance Company.
Scope and Content
Records, 1849-1954, of the Mutual Fire Insurance Company of Loudoun County, located in Waterford, Virginia. Includes accounts, agent collection books, applications and indexes, cancelled policy ledgers, correspondence, day books, losses paid, minute books of the Board of Directors and Executive Committee, policy certificates, premium indexes, risk books, securities purchased and sold, short term risk books, treasurer's records, and architectural drawings of the company's home office.
The bulk of the collection consists of applications for insurance. They include the applicant's name, residence, value(s) of dwelling house, furniture, storage house and goods, mill, and barn. Other information provided by the applicant includes location of the building(s) to be insured, of what material it is constructed, if the structure is occupied, size of the building, number of chimneys, distances between neighboring buildings, if incumbered, and for how much, and whether there is any insurance presently on it. Occasionally, there is correspondence with the applicant. The applications are arranged numerically, and are indexed in separate volumes.
The minute books also contain financial accounts of the company's secretary and treasurer, and lists of company assets. The volumes were microfilmed for preservation purposes, and are contained on six reels. MISC. REEL 4562: Minute Book, 25 May 1849-1 May 1871; MISC. REEL 4563: Minute Book, 1 May 1871 (cont.)-9 August 1879, and Minute Book, 25 August 1879-17 December 1885; MISC. REEL 4564: Minute Book, 8 January 1886-9 January 1894, and Minute Book, 19 January 1894-20 June 1906; MISC. REEL 4565: Minute Book, 23 July 1906-18 April 1922, and Minute Book, 14 May 1922-7 November 1933; MISC. REEL 4566: Minute Book, 21 November 1933-29 December 1953; MISC. REEL 4567: Act of Incorporation, Constititution & By-Laws (Amended), 1897, and Letterbook, 1885-1907.
Contents List
- Account Ledger, ca. 1930's-1950's
- Accounts, ca. 1930's-1950's
- Agent Collection Books, 1940-1941
- Agent Collection Books, 1940, 1948
- Agent Collection Books, 1941-1942
- Agent Collection Books, 1943-1946
- Agent Collection Books, 1946-1948
- Agent Collection Books, 1949
- Agent Collection Books, 1950-1951
- Agent Collection Books, ca. 1940's-1950's
- Agent Collection Books, ca. 1940's-1950's
- Agent Record Book, ca. 1888-1901
- Agent Record Book, ca. 1901-1905
- Agent Record Book, 1905-1909
- Agent Record Book, 1906-1908
- Agent Record Book, ca. 1910-1915
- Agent Record Book, ca. 1937-1950's
- Applications, 2-800
- Applications, 1501-2200
- Applications, 2201-3200
- Applications, 2701-3800
- Applications, 3201-4300
- Applications, 4301-5400
- Applications, 8001-8500; 10301-10600
- Applications, 10601-11700
- Applications, 11701-12600
- Applications, 12601-12800; 13601-13700; 21651-22100
- Applications, 12801-13600
- Applications, 13701-14400
- Applications, 14401-16400
- Applications, 16401-18400
- Applications, 18401-19600
- Applications, 19601-20200
- Applications, 20201-21000
- Applications, 21001-21650
- Applications, 22101-24000
- Applications, 24001-25175
- Applications, 24601-25800
- Applications, 25801-26900
- Applications, 26901-27600
- Applications, 27601-28350
- Applications, 28351-28700; 29301-29625
- Applications, 28701-29300
- Applications, 29626-30375
- Applications, 30376-31100
- Applications, 31101-32000
- Applications, 32001-32700
- Applications, 32601-33625
- Applications, 32701-33600
- Applications, 33601-34400
- Applications, 33701-34700
- Applications, 34401-36100
- Applications, 36101-37020
- Applications, 37021-37700
- Applications, 37701-38575
- Applications, 37701-39400
- Applications, 38576-39400
- Applications, 39401-41200
- Applications, 39401-39900, 40826-41200
- Applications, 39901-40825
- Applications, 41201-42000
- Applications, 41201-43000
- Applications, 42001-43000
- Applications, 43001-43550
- Applications, 43551-44225
- Applications, 44226-44700
- Applications, 44701-45800
- Applications, 45301-45400, 45801-46300
- Applications, 46301-47200
- Applications, 47201-47700
- Applications, 47701-49300
- Applications, 47801-48160
- Applications, 48161-48900
- Applications, 71601-72125
- Applications, 72126-72900
- Applications, A301-A1600
- Applications, A1601-A2000
- Applications, A2001-A2700
- Applications, A2701-A3200
- Applications, A3201-A3800
- Applications, A3801-A5000
- Applications, A5001-A6200
- Applications, A6201-A7500
- Applications, A7501-A7800
- Applications, A7801-A9000
- Applications, A8001-A8700
- Applications, A9001-A10100
- Applications, A11201-A12000
- Applications, A13601-A14300
- Applications, A14301-A14800
- Applications, A11201-A12000
- Applications, A13601-A14300
- Applications, A13601-A14300
- Applications, A17301-A17900
- Applications, A17301-A18500
- Applications, A17901-A18500
- Applications, A18501-A19700
- Applications, A19701-A20800
- Applications, A20801-A21900
- Applications, A21901-A23100
- Applications, A23200-A24900
- Applications, A24901-A26900
- Applications, A26901-A29100
- Applications, A29100-A30200
- Applications, A29601-A30700
- Applications, A30701-A31900
- Applications, A31901-A32600
- Applications, A34701-A36500
- Applications, A36501-A37200
- Applications, A36501-A38200
- Applications, A37301-A38200
- Applications, A38201-A39700
- Applications, A39701-A41400
- Applications, A41401-A43200
- Applications, A43201-A44800
- Applications, A44801-A46700
- Applications, A46301-A47000
- Applications, A46701-A47800
- Applications, A47001-A47800
- Applications, A47801-A49200
- Applications, A50801-A51400
- Applications, A51401-A52300
- Applications, A52301-A53800
- Applications, A53801-A55200
- Applications, A54101-A54900
- Applications, A54901-A55200, A53801-A54100
- Applications, A55201-A56000
- Applications, A55201-A56700
- Applications, A56001-A56700
- Applications, A56701-A58100
- Applications, unsorted
- Applications, unsorted
- Applications, unsorted
- Architectural Drawings - Exterior Stair Addition, 1 sheet (Located at LVA-downtown branch).
- Architectural Drawings - Home Office, 22 sheets (Located at LVA-downtown branch).
- Architectural Drawings - Home Office Landscape Plan, 1 sheet (Located at LVA-downtown branch).
- Architectural Drawings - Home Office Perspective Drawings, 2 sheets (Located at LVA-downtown branch).
- Architectural Drawings - Home Office Rendering, 1 sheet (Located at LVA-downtown branch).
- Architectural Drawings - Home Office Specifications (Located at LVA-downtown branch).
- Architectural Drawings - Home Office Tracings, 21 sheets (Located at LVA-downtown branch).
- Architectural Drawings - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Receipts for Landscaping (Located at LVA-downtown branch).
- Architectural Drawings - Sketches of Design for Home Office, 6 sheets (Located at LVA-downtown branch).
- Cancelled Policy Ledger, 1895-1902
- Cancelled Policy Ledger, 1902-1906
- Cancelled Policy Ledger, 1906-1911
- Cancelled Policy Ledger, 1914
- Cancelled Policy Ledger, 1925
- Cancelled Policy Ledger, 1934-1938
- Cancelled Policy Ledger, 1938-1941
- Cancelled Policy Ledger, 1941-1945
- Cancelled Policy Ledger, 1945-1948
- Cancelled Policy Ledger, 1948-1954
- Correspondence, ca. 1930's-1940's
- Correspondence and Losses, 1940's
- Daybook, 1890-1923
- Daybook, 1899-1905
- Daybook, 1905-1910
- Daybook, 1910-1917
- Daybook, 1917-1923
- Daybook, 1923-1929
- Daybook, 1924-1936
- Daybook, 1929-1935
- Daybook, 1936-1940
- Daybook, 1937-1948
- Daybook, 1940-1944
- Daybook, 1944-1947
- Daybook, 1949-1959
- Daybook, 1951-1954
- Index to Applications
- Index to Applications
- Index to Applications
- Index to Applications
- Index to Applications
- Index to Applications
- Index to Applications
- Ledger, 1881-1893
- Ledger, 1893-1906
- Ledger, 1905-1924
- Ledger, 1925-1935
- Losses, 1924-1929
- Losses Paid, 1899-1901, 1913-1914
- Losses Paid, 1902-1906
- Losses Paid, 1903, 1937-1938, 1949
- Losses Paid, 1906-1908
- Losses Paid, 1909-1912
- Losses Paid, 1915-1921
- Losses Paid, 1919-1924
- Losses Paid, 1925-1935
- Losses Paid, 1929-1932
- Losses Paid, 1932-1933, 1935, 1937
- Losses Paid, 1938-1940, 1944-1945
- Losses Paid, 1940-1941, 1954
- Losses Paid, 1940's
- Losses Paid, 1940's
- Losses Paid, 1954
- Map - Loudoun County, by Yardley Taylor, 1853 (Located at LVA-downtown branch).
- Map - Waterford, Loudoun County, Virginia, from Surveys by James S. Oden, 1875 (Located at LVA-downtown branch. Also available on compact disc - CD 199, LVA Lab #10_0631).
- Map - United States, by Griffiths Johnson, 1857 (Located at LVA-downtown branch).
- Merchant's Book, 1880's-1890's
- Minute Book, 25 May 1849 - 1 May 1871 (Misc. Reel 4562-4563)
- Minute Book, 25 August 1879 - 17 December 1885 (Misc. Reel 4563)
- Minute Book, 8 January 1886 - 9 January 1894 (Misc. Reel 4564)
- Minute Book, 19 January 1894 - 20 June 1906 (Misc. Reel 4564)
- Minute Book, 23 July 1906 - 18 April 1922 (Misc. Reel 4565)
- Minute Book, 14 May 1922 - 7 November 1933 (Misc. Reel 4565)
- Minute Book, 21 November 1933 - 29 December 1953 (Misc. Reel 4566)
- Act of Incorporation, Constititution and By-Laws (Amended), 1897, and Letterbook, 1885-1907 (Misc. Reel 4567)
- Miscellaneous - Edward Nichols Papers, 1913-1914
- Policy Certificates, 1940's-1950's
- Policy Certificates, 1940's-1950's
- Premium Index 1
- Premium Index 1 Culpeper/Frederick
- Premium Index 1 Fairfax/Clarke/Prince William
- Premium Index 1 Loudoun Agency
- Premium Index 1 Miscellaneous
- Premium Index 1 Rockingham/Augusta
- Premium Index 2 Clarke/Prince William
- Premium Index 2 Culpeper Agency
- Premium Index 2 Fairfax/Arlington
- Premium Index 2 Frederick Agency
- Premium Index 2 Loudoun
- Premium Index 2 Miscellaneous
- Premium Index 2 Shenandoah/Augusta
- Premium Index 2 Warren/Fauquier Agencies
- Premium Index 3 Clarke/Prince William
- Premium Index 3 Culpeper Agencies
- Premium Index 3 Fairfax/Arlington Agencies
- Premium Index 3 Frederick Agency
- Premium Index 3 Loudoun
- Premium Index 3 Miscellaneous Agencies
- Premium Index 3 Shenandoah/Augusta
- Premium Index 3 Warrenton/Fauquier Agencies
- Premium Notebook, 1884-1890's
- Premium Notebook, 1888
- Premium Notebook, 1893
- Premium Notebook, 1898
- Premium Notebook, 1913
- Premium Notebook, 1918
- Record of Losses by Fire and Lightning, 1903-1940
- Risk Book, 1873-1884
- Risk Book, 1884-1890
- Risk Book, 1890-1894
- Risk Book, 1894-1899
- Risk Book, 1899-1903
- Risk Book, 1903-1906
- Risk Book, 1906
- Risk Book B
- Risk Book C
- Risk Book D
- Risk Book E
- Risk Book F
- Risk Book G
- Risk Book H
- Risk Book I
- Risk Book J
- Risk Book K
- Risk Book L
- Risk Book M
- Risk Book N
- Risk Book O
- Risk Book P
- Risk Book Q
- Risk Book
- Risk Book
- Risk Book
- Securities Purchased and Sold, 1929-1930
- Short Term Risks, 1888-1918
- Short Term Risks, 1918-1929
- Short Term Risks, 1928
- Treasurer's Day Book, 1851-1899
- Treasurer's Day Book, 1891-1923
- Treasuer's Ledger, 1851-1902
- Treasurer's Ledger, 1903-1927
- Treasurer's Ledger, 1920's-1930's